This is Software Engineering Radio, the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at SE-Radio.net.
SE Radio is brought to you by the IEEE
Computer Society and by IEEE Software
Magazine online at
computer.org/software.
>> Hello and welcome to Software
Engineering Radio. This is your host
Arun Ponnusamy.
Today I'm joined by Will Wilson, CEO and
co-founder of Antithesis. Will started
off in biotech and went on to work on
distributed systems at FoundationDB,
Apple, and Google.
And then he eventually went on to found
Antithesis, an autonomous testing
platform based on deterministic
simulation testing.
Will, welcome to the show.
>> Thank you so much for having me.
>> For our listeners who may not be
familiar with the concept, could you
share what is DST or deterministic
simulation testing?
>> Yeah, sure. So, let's start with the way
that people normally test software,
right? So, the way they normally test
software is first you write some code,
and then you try and think about what
situations you want to cover with a
test, what situations you want to make
sure are going to work in real life, and
then you write some tests to cover those
situations, right? And then you
occasionally run those tests, maybe you
do them on every CI build, or maybe you
do them on every PR, maybe you do them
only when you're about to release your
software,
but they cover those cases, and you hope
that when you deploy to production,
everything is going to go okay. Now, let
me ask you a question. Do you believe if
all your tests pass, that everything is
going to be okay?
>> I would like to think so.
>> But do you actually?
>> Uh well, if anything last 20 years have
shown me, no.
>> Right, right. Exactly, so why is that?
Well, it's because we, I just said,
you're writing the tests that cover the
cases that you thought were important to
cover. But the things that are actually
going to screw you in production are the
situations that you did not think of
ahead of time. They're the things you
did not think to cover, right? And so
what that means is this conventional
strategy to writing tests is very very
good for catching regressions, right? If
there's something that I know my
software does correctly and I
accidentally break it in a new version,
if I have a test for it, that's a pretty
good at catching that. But a test is
very bad at finding out if my software
actually works in the real world in all
the unanticipated or unexpected
situations that the real world will
throw at me.
So, deterministic simulation testing is
a very different strategy, which tries
to actually give us the confidence that
if our test pass,
things will go well in the real world.
And the way it does that is basically by
constructing a model of the real world,
a whole system simulation
where random requests come in and ask
your software to do things and tasks are
going to run in random orders and these
requests are going to have slightly
randomized parameters. And also the
things that happen in the real world
that can go wrong are also going to
happen, right? So, occasionally requests
will fail. Requests to downstream
dependent systems will fail. Network
requests may get delayed or reordered.
Threads may randomly pause and run
later. The garbage collector may just
turn on and that whole node may slow
down, right? All the stuff that causes
people to get paged in the middle of the
night and causes weird production
behaviors that nobody can understand,
we're going to do all that, too. And
we're going to do it at a vastly
accelerated rate so that we cover many
many years or centuries worth of real
world badness in just a few seconds or
minutes in our tests. And if our
software survives all that and things
actually go okay, we're now going to
have the confidence to actually deploy
and to actually feel like things will be
all right when we have it in the real
world.
The
final ingredient to this, the part that
makes it deterministic
is our model of the real world, unlike
the real world, is perfectly
deterministic. Meaning it's all driven
from a random number generator that's
under our control, right? So, this is
very important because sometimes what
happens is there's a particular
Let's say that a packet takes 21
milliseconds to get from service A to
service B. And if it takes 19
milliseconds instead, something goes
wrong, right? There's some distributed
race condition. Something something
loses and as a result there's some bug
that a user can see.
You may have great difficulty
replicating that situation again, right?
Maybe it only happened it only took that
long because of some very rare set of
circumstances.
But the determinism of DST means that
any set of circumstances, no matter how
rare, no matter how unusual, we can
perfectly replicate. And so if we see a
bug once, we can see it as many times as
we want and we can debug it with very
very high efficiency.
How you actually achieve that is sort of
the hard part. But once you have it,
it's an incredible asset.
>> Awesome, thank you. Before I dive in, I
would like to get some of the origin
stories here. I hear it started off in
FoundationDB. Could you share some of
that background there?
>> Sure, yeah. So, this is sort of a fun
story. Basically, actually even before
FoundationDB, my co-founder Dave
Scherer, before FoundationDB, had
another company called Visual Sciences,
which you can think of as having made a
very very early web analytics product
that was backed by a very powerful
analytic database that's sort of a very
early version of Google BigQuery, right?
And this would have been in the early
2000s. So, it was really very very ahead
of its time.
So, when Dave was building that big
analytic data store, he was really
interested in using model-based
techniques to look for sort of long-tail
performance pathologies and like strange
sort of high latency corner cases.
And so he built this little like model
based simulation of the database
to see if he could find these issues.
It's sort of like in some ways similar
to formal methods if you're familiar
with that, but he was using it to
analyze performance rather than
correctness.
The problem that Dave ran into was of
course once he had this all working in
the model
how do you know that your real code is
behaving anything like the model, right?
And so that company got sold and and
that never went anywhere and but it
stuck around in the back of his mind.
And so then when we were doing
FoundationDB he had the same idea again
this time to use it to study correctness
rather than performance.
But then he had the further idea what if
we just made the actual program into the
model, right? Then you would never have
to worry that oh I did some analysis on
this model and it gave me this result,
but actually my real world code has a
bug in it so it doesn't perfectly match
that specification.
So the trouble is you know real world
code has things like concurrency and it
has things like it reads the clock and
it gets random numbers from the
operating system and it it does all
kinds of things that make it
fundamentally non-deterministic and make
it so that if you run some battery of
tests or conduct some simulation
the result might vary from time to time.
And so we set about writing FoundationDB
in a very special way so that it could
be perfectly simulated. We did things
like we used our own user space
concurrency primitives and scheduling so
that the kernel was never deciding which
task to run. It's like sort of similar
to the Node.js concurrency model, but we
were doing that in C++ long beforehand.
We obviously had to mock out or stub out
any form of network communication
between nodes and handle that in
process. We had a fake clock and a fake
random number generator that got
accessed instead of the ones provided by
the OS. And as we sort of knocked away
each of these forms of randomness and
each of these forms of non-determinism,
the simulation became more controllable
until we eventually got to a point where
it really was like you could really just
run a program and it would simulate an
entire interacting FoundationDB cluster
with possibly dozens or hundreds of
simulated nodes speaking over simulated
networks with, you know, randomly
introduced networking delays and
congestion behavior and whatever else
you want. And this was just such an
insanely
productive mode in which to work. Like
people who are familiar with
FoundationDB these days mostly know it
for its reputation, which is being one
of the highest quality databases ever
made, never losing your data, never
doing anything wrong. And it's true, we
got that. And we got that because of
this technique. But the thing that made
almost an even bigger difference was
that we were able to get that with a
very, very small team.
Because what this technique enables is
like this incredible form
of pair programming with the computer
where you write some code and then you
run some simulations and you say, "Did I
introduce any bugs?" And, you know, if
the answer is yes, then like you just
try again. It's like having an oracle or
a genie that can tell you if your code
is correct, right? It's like this
incredible, incredible accelerator for
an entire team. And that was what made
us really excited about this technique
and I think this is why so many others
have started adopting it and picking it
up as well.
>> Interesting.
That reminds me as you go deeper, right?
I mean
to really simulation, you need a model.
So, how do you avoid the paradox of hey
look, I don't know what I don't know and
I build this model?
>> Yeah, that is a really, really good
question. And basically, the answer is
you have to err a little bit on the side
of your model being worse than reality,
rather than better than reality, right?
>> Could you give an example of that, what
worse looks like?
>> Yeah, sure. So, your network in your
data center is occasionally going to
have periods of being down, and it's
going to occasionally have periods where
it's a little bit slow, and it's
occasionally going to have periods where
it's like working great. And these
periods in your network are probably
totally uncorrelated with what your
program is doing, right? And so, suppose
that there's some bug, and the bug only
happens if your program is in the middle
of some particular operation, right?
Like you you're doing some I don't know,
you're doing some transaction on your
database, and at exactly that moment,
the network does something a little bit
wrong, right? Or it's a little bit
slower than you expect, or whatever. And
only if these two things happen at the
same time, this bug happens. And let's
say the bug is really, really bad.
In order to make that bug happen very
reliably and very reproducibly in our
tests,
we don't want to make the network
completely uncorrelated from what your
program is doing. We want to make it
basically as malicious as it can be,
right? We want to try making the network
bad at each different sort of moment
that your program could be doing
something,
and we want to like artificially
increase the probability that this
network badness happens at exactly the
right spot to trigger that bug. Because
that way you see it in your test like in
a few seconds or a few minutes, rather
than having to wait for days or weeks,
which you would have to do if it were
happening in production. And so, that's
kind of an example of where if you make
the simulation
more hostile than reality, it can catch
stuff
quicker than it would happen in the real
world, and also ensures that you don't
miss things that That happen in the real
world.
>> Mhm. So, what would be a good
I suppose
evaluation or identification function to
know when or what a bad network is. For
example, a network loss of 10% may be
really good in some applications, but
really bad in some. So, how do you
decide
>> That's totally true. And furthermore,
there can be a very dangerous pattern,
where if you basically make these
parameters a like a little bit wrong,
right? You could accidentally get
yourself in a situation where the
simulation isn't really testing
anything.
Right? Consider the corner case where we
just make it so the network never
transports anything at all. Now, your
program never does anything. And then
all your tests are green because we
didn't find any bugs because your
program didn't do anything. That would
be a bad outcome, right?
And so, there's a few techniques that we
can use to to avoid this and to make the
simulation really good and really
well-tuned instead. One is just let's
look at things like code coverage, or
the more sophisticated version of this
is like behavioral coverage, right? If
you have certain corner cases in your
code that you know are interesting and
are important to cover, you should just
log a little message when that situation
happens. And then at the end of a test
run, we should make an assertion that
we're able to see all those messages,
right? That we basically got at some
point to every one of those situations.
And the generalization of that is
something that we call sometimes
assertions. They're like the dual or the
opposite of normal assertions, right?
Rather than asserting that something is
always or never happening, we're
asserting that it sometimes happens
because that's an important indication
about whether our test is working
effectively.
>> Is that in a probabilistic model or is
it truly sometimes?
>> Right, right. So, it's like at least
one, right? We're saying that if I run
my program a thousand times,
I want to guarantee that I see this
behavior at least once. That is a
property of my testing system, right?
It's like I should be able to make the
situation occur. Like the ultimate
guarantor though is just like are you
still seeing bugs in production?
Basically, I think people regardless of
whether doing DST or not, if you ever
see a bug in production that is actually
two bugs.
It's a bug in your program and it's also
a bug in your tests and you should maybe
not solve them in that order. Maybe you
should solve the bug in your test first.
Who knows what else it will turn up.
And this is like a very This is a a
practice that requires a little bit of
discipline to get into, but once you do,
it's it's so incredibly powerful. Just
like understand why it is that you
didn't see that bug the minute it was
introduced. And often it will point to
an entire area of your
of your software or of your organization
or whatever that is not working
correctly.
>> Mhm. So it it sounded like there was a
bootstrap phase here for a team to kind
of onboard. Let's let's say I'm writing
a game, right? A multiplayer game
running on the internet. It's probably
as low level as it gets, right?
What would the bootstrap phase for me be
to adopt this?
>> Right, so
this gets a little bit into like sort of
what our company does.
Basically, up until we came around,
this technique was very very powerful,
but it was a giant pain to adopt because
it required you to do things like mock
out your dependencies and somehow take
control of like concurrency and
scheduling within your program, simulate
all of your network connections, right?
There there's sort of a lot that had to
be done. And there were applications and
use cases where
reliability and correctness was so
important that people
would do all these things. Like I I know
of actually quite a large number of
people now cuz they they come talk to
me, right? Who actually started doing
this in the years after FoundationDB got
acquired by Apple. The team at Dropbox
that worked on their synchronization
technology built their own DST. Tiger
Beetle is a very well-known financial
transactions database. They built their
own DST. It's It's quite good.
You know, a number of people actually in
the finance or fintech or or crypto
space built their own DST and did very
good job at it because they really
wanted to catch any kind of problem
before it hit prod because it could
result in losing tons of money. And
obviously other database vendors were
also doing this as were a number of
teams that got influenced by what we had
done at FoundationDB. And by the way,
after I went to work at Google, I
learned that there were teams inside
Google that had done this and just never
told anybody about it. So, I think this
is a technique that's been independently
reinvented a few times.
But,
it remained a thing that only very very
committed people
who really felt like their program had
to be perfectly reliable would do
because the adoption costs were high.
So,
our new company, Antithesis, tries to
drastically reduce the adoption cost for
this style of testing by basically
doing like solving two of the problems
that you and I have already discussed.
One is how do you take an arbitrary
collection of software and make it
deterministic, right? And
prior to to us being around, that took a
lot of work. And what we've done is
write a hypervisor, which is
deterministic. And you can take an
arbitrary collection of software and
just put it in the hypervisor, and now
it's deterministic, too.
And so, that already on its own makes
this much easier.
The second problem is the one you
touched on, which is what's the right
network drop rate, right? What is the
right way of tuning all these parameters
of the simulation to find all the bugs
and to find those quickly as possible.
This is like a very hard optimization
machine learning science problem. And
it's sort of unreasonable in my opinion
for every team on earth to try and solve
this independently. And so we have also
just done a huge amount of research and
a huge amount of
development to make this simulation like
self-tuning and to make it very
intelligent and very good at finding the
correct parameters and the correct
settings. So you just don't even have to
think about that.
And so the goal here is to make it much
much much easier for people to adopt
this stuff which hopefully just makes
them a lot faster at writing software
and also produce much higher quality
software.
>> I want to quickly touch back on a point
you mentioned about the cost, right?
What would the cost for these
organizations to adopt DST in their own
setting engineering wise, financially?
>> Yeah, I think if you don't have a
solution like antithesis, then the the
question is really dominated by your
dependencies. Right? Because the hard
thing about DST
is that
unless you have a hypervisor, you need
to somehow make it so all your
dependencies are deterministic too.
And that like really does just hugely
limit
what you can do. Most software in the
world is not deterministic, right? It's
got concurrency, it's got threads, it it
checks timers, it does all kinds of
stuff. When we were developing
FoundationDB,
we were so influenced by this DST style
of development that we actually started
removing our dependencies to make it
easier to test in this way. So
very early versions of our database were
using Apache Zookeeper for coordination
for instance. And that just became a
thing that we could no longer accept
because it made it harder to simulate.
And so we deleted Zookeeper and wrote
our own Paxos implementation that could
be simulated and that made sense for us.
But that's a very, very hard thing to
ask somebody to do if they're just
starting to adopt this technology, which
is one reason that I think that thus far
it's only been it's only happened in
relatively specialized places.
>> It's almost like asking them to
re-reinvent or re-implement what you
what you guys are doing.
>> Yeah, that's right. It's it's just it's
just a very high barrier to entry and
that's what we're trying to fix.
>> Fair enough. That brings me back to the
hypervisor that you have mentioned. I
mean, can you tell me more about that?
>> Sure. So
we started from the question of how
could we make DST easy to adopt? And
it's like, well, we need to make it so
that everybody can make their program
deterministic super easily. And then
it's like, well
you know, if your program is written in
Java, you could try and make a
deterministic JVM. And if your program's
written in C, I guess you could try and
make a deterministic Linux user space,
right? Actually, Facebook did that. That
project's called Hermit.
But we're going to have customers who
use every language. So we can't just
like play whack-a-mole here doing all
these things.
And then it's like, well, so much of the
value is being able to test
microservices where service A is talking
to service B over a network. But now we
need to make that networking
deterministic. How are we going to do
that? Like, oh wow, we need some crazy
networking library that we can drop in,
but everybody does networking
differently. How do we Right, like so
very, very quickly
you get to like, well
I guess we should try and get under all
of these things and make a deterministic
operating system.
But then you hit another problem. Well,
first of all, not everybody in the world
uses Linux and we would love to be able
to have customers on Windows someday and
and so on. But also the
interface between the Linux kernel and
everything running on top of it is
really complicated. And it's always
changing. Right?
And so
maintaining a perfect deterministic
Linux
as a small company
just seemed like a very tall order.
And then we were like, you know what?
You know what is a very simple interface
that has not changed in 40 50 years?
The x86 CPU instructions. Like look, so
let's just get under the operating
system
and let's let's emulate a deterministic
computer.
Where no matter what the operating
system does, no matter what interrupts
it sets, no matter how it, you know, is
managing memory or doing anything
from the outside, or rather from the
inside, it it's like living in a perfect
isolated hermetic deterministic universe
and it it can't actually cause any
non-determinism.
And then once you build that
it's like so easy to adopt. Now people
don't have to change their software at
all. They just give it to us, we run it
inside the magic box, and it's perfectly
deterministic. So it's it's really very
very powerful.
>> How does this overcome the I mean this
box is still in isolation or
is external to your TCP stack itself or
or the network layer itself? So how do
you reconcile that?
>> Right. So basically what we do is we
take our customers' multiple
microservices, right? Representing a
bunch of different physical nodes in
their in their compute back end.
Plus whatever their dependencies are.
Maybe they have a database or maybe
they've got some API server or whatever.
And we take them all and we put them
inside the same guest in operating
system environment, which is Linux. And
then we connect them over TCP locally
inside the VM. Right? So they can speak
over network connections between
different Docker containers running all
in the same version of Linux.
And then we can actually reach in and
interfere with those network
connections, right? We can slow the
packets, we can drop packets, we can we
can do whatever. We can create simulated
partitions, we can and we can correlate
all this with the code that's running,
right? The thing I told you before.
Because we see what code is running cuz
we control the operating system. And so
it's actually
it's actually a very complete solution.
It works very well. The one thing that's
a little bit of friction is if you are
highly dependent on some third-party web
service that you cannot put in a
container and have a hard time mocking.
That is going to cause a problem. So we
try and reduce that friction for our
customers also by writing very good,
very high-quality mocks for a lot of
common web services. So for example, we
have a whole fake AWS that we can like
run inside the simulation with you. And
if your program uses AWS, it just runs
in there and uses the fake one and can't
even tell the difference. We actually
test our own stuff that way cuz we're
very heavy AWS users.
We can do the same for Snowflake and GCP
and Stripe and you know, whatever. We
can write a good mock for it. And that's
that's nice because basically just a few
of those covers the vast majority of
APIs that people use.
And if there's a long tail, you know, I
think we'll we'll get to it someday.
The other thing that the hypervisor
gives us, which is very, very powerful,
is
extremely efficient and rapid
snapshotting and restore of the whole
state of the guest operating system.
Right? So if you use a VMware
hypervisor, for instance, you can like
snapshot that VM and then you can reload
it, right? And that that takes a little
bit of time, but you can do it. Our
hypervisor is optimized to perform that
operation incredibly quickly and
efficiently.
More than that even, when it's running
multiple VMs simultaneously on the same
computer, those VMs can actually address
the same physical memory
if
their local version of that memory
hasn't changed. Right? So we're
basically doing copy-on-write on all of
the memory of the guest operating
system. So, now if we run 100 VMs in
parallel on the same machine, they're
not using 100 times the memory. We're
basically like deduplicating all of the
memory between all the different VMs,
which is a thing that I don't know
anybody else's hypervisor can do that.
I'm sure there is one somewhere. But,
what it means is that we can now test
your stuff really efficiently, right?
Cuz we can use huge amounts of
parallelism without drastically
increasing the memory requirements,
which just at the end of the day means
that we can find bugs faster, and we can
find rare bugs faster.
>> It's interesting because the implication
of this means that
a, you kind of running the entire
customer world in a single sandbox.
And you can also do things like simulate
connection between A and B
if it was in the same zone or same
region or even across regions.
Because you want to know that, hey,
look, this is for DR and for various
kinds of uh a fault tolerance, right?
>> That's exactly right. All that we have
to do is really change the latency,
right? On the virtual connection. Or we
>> And error rates.
>> And error rates, that's right. And also,
you know, correlated failures, right?
We'll make things in the same DR region
fail together more often, but not across
regions. And people use us to test DR
all the time. People also love using us
to test live upgrades. Cuz that's a very
scary situation for many teams. You have
some big service deployed, and you have
customers who are using it, right? And
you want to incrementally upgrade your
cluster. And while the upgrade is
rolling out, you're going to have
servers with both the old version and
the new version serving requests
simultaneously.
Does that all work? It can be very hard
to test that. But, it's quite easy to
test it with our environment.
>> Interesting. So, two things here from a
quote-unquote cost perspective.
What is the biggest installation that
you run so far on this? Like, you know,
how many services, how many instances,
RAM,
cores?
>> Yeah. So, the biggest one that I know of
So we have a customer WarpStream, which
was recently acquired by Confluent.
Yeah, so I think they may be our largest
one. So So they develop like a Kafka
replacement with blob storage on S3,
right? And so we started out just
testing their Kafka replacement and and
making sure that that was good and the
things that were really durable were
really durable and and so on.
And then what happened was they added
all the rest of their SaaS architecture
into the simulation as well. So the same
simulation is not just testing their
Kafka and their operations with S3 and
so on. It's also testing like user
sign-ups and like, you know, people
using their admin APIs to like create
clusters and it's like totally crazy. It
is actually far beyond what I've ever
done with DST, but it works.
>> How big was it?
>> I would have to go look it up. I do not
know the answer off the top of my head.
But I But I think there were like a many
many many different services involved.
>> Okay. Fair enough. In terms of their own
testing phase, typically how long do
customers run this for? Is it a parallel
thing? Is it a ongoing thing? What is
the workflow for them?
>> Yeah, that's a great question. So I
think there's two main
ways that people do this. And one of our
long-term product goals, actually not
even long-term, one of our relatively
short-term now product goals is to
bridge these two ways of using it. So
the first way people use this is sort of
offline as a very intensive check phase,
maybe overnight, right? Or maybe like
they do tons and tons of testing right
before release, before rolling out a
release, right? So the idea here is like
you spend all day writing code and then
whatever the last version of your code
is, the default branch, you send that to
us when people leave work and then we
test it all night and then in the
morning you come in and you see what
your results are. And that can be cool.
It does mean that we can find pretty
rare, pretty hard-to-find bugs because
we're testing for 12 hours or whatever.
And but they're still fresh in your head
and it's probably code that you changed
yesterday, so it's still high
productivity to work on those problems.
The other way of using it, which is much
more similar to the way that we used it
at FoundationDB,
well, I guess we actually did both
there. But But the other way of using it
is
in the loop, right? Like while you're
coding. So, you write some code, you
make some change, you kick off a test.
And hopefully, if you want to do it this
way, you need to make it so that your
tests can run very fast or can give you
good information very quickly. So that
hopefully, like within 15 minutes or
maybe an hour at most, you get some
answer that's like
was there anything obviously broken
this, right? And that can be a very,
very powerful iteration loop.
I think the ideal
is to have both. And moreover, to have
them be working together. It would be
cool if, like, for example, you are
submitting builds throughout the day and
you're you're running tests on them. And
anything which at the end of the day
you're still iterating on, but which was
green, which we didn't find a bug yet,
overnight, we do like hundreds more
hours of simulation, CPU hours, and look
much more deeply for bugs in any of
those versions, then give you a report
when you get in in the morning, and then
you can sort of pick up where you left
off. I think that would be really cool,
and and that's sort of what we're aiming
to get towards.
>> Hm, interesting.
>> Can your software engineering team plan,
track, and ship faster? monday.dev says
yes.
With monday.dev, you get fully
customizable workflows, AI-powered
context, and integrations that work
within your IDE.
No more admin bottlenecks, no add-ons,
no BS. Just a frictionless platform
built for developers.
Try for free at monday.com/dev.
You'll love it.
>> You brought up correlation with the code
base earlier.
Tell me more. At what level is the
correlation? Is it at the compiled
binary level? Is it at actual source
code level based on coverage? How does
that work?
>> Right. So, basically, we have very good
integration with a large number of
different language toolchains. So, it
works a little differently depending on
the language. Some of the languages we
actually just come in and like transform
your binary afterwards, and you don't
have to do anything at all. Like, we do
that for Java. Other languages, like, we
give you some flags that you pass to
your compiler. Like, for instance, we do
this for C++ and Rust. And the result in
either case is
is the same binary that you would run in
production, except it tells us
when each line of code gets reached,
right? So far, this is very similar for
with instrumenting for code coverage or
something like that.
But, the thing is the key is we're not
just going to use this for reporting
coverage to you. We're also going to use
this for this kind of correlation stuff,
for saying, "Oh, we're in like code
block A. We've never tried pausing a
thread while we're in code block A
before. Let's do that now." Or like,
"Oh, this microservice is running
function X,
and simultaneously this other one over
here is also running function X. Let's
interrupt the network connection between
them right now and see what happens,
right?" And we're going to do that very
much in parallel. And then, the fact
that the hypervisor lets us cheaply
snapshot and restore stuff means that we
can go back to situations that we found
interesting and try exploring more from
that point. And that basically lets us
amplify the probability of very, very
rare events to find really, really hard
to discover bugs. I'll give you a
concrete example because that was a
little bit vague. Suppose you have a bug
and in order for this bug to happen
you need to be in the middle of a
transaction rollback
and there needs to be some network
problem
and right at that moment something has
to trigger a leader election in your
cluster or something.
If each of those events has a one in
1,000 chance of happening at any given
moment, that's like a one in a billion
bug, right? That's like very, very hard
for a test to find normally.
But if you're running it in production
and you're running on thousands of nodes
and whatever, like your customers will
totally hit that bug. So this is like a
classic example of a bug that normal
testing would never, ever find and that
would cause you to get in a page. And
so, but what we can do because we can
see what code is running is when we hit
that one in 1,000 transaction rollback,
we're going to say, "Aha, we made a
transaction rollback. We've never seen
that before." Let's do more testing from
this point onwards. And each of the
tries we do from that point, if it
doesn't hit the next event of interest,
we can just reset to the transaction
rollback and try more stuff from there,
right? It's like if you're playing a
computer game and you can save your game
anytime you want it's easier to make
progress because you can always just
reload your game and and go to the point
where things were going well.
And so
basically what this means is that for
these bugs that require multiple
different rare things to happen in
sequence, we can find them at a vastly
accelerated rate compared to traditional
techniques.
>> You know, I love the example of the
saving the game and going back again. I
spent my '90s doing that in all those
old games.
>> Yeah, well, so we actually use computer
games a lot for our testing our DST. So
we believe that a good testing system
should be able to beat a computer game
in the interest of testing it. And
indeed, if you go to our website, we
have many videos of Antithesis playing
classic computer games and beating them.
>> I saw the uh Mario example at S Recon
last year.
So, back to the example, right? So, what
what you said was when you hit that one
in a thousand transaction rollback
scenario,
you still need that scenario to be hit.
Is there a way you can kind of say like
this block of code actually through some
sequence of code paths
could get hit, and can you force that to
happen proactively instead of waiting
for it?
>> So, that's a great question. We try very
hard to make it so that everything gets
hit, and there's a number of techniques
that we use to do that, right? One is a
very, I think very underused technique
called swarm testing, which is
applicable to people who are not even
doing DST. Just everybody needs to know
about this technique. Okay.
And so, the the the basic idea of swarm
testing is
you sometimes should run all of your
tests with certain features of your
program turned off.
That sounds counterintuitive, right? Why
would you want to do that? Well, imagine
a situation where, let's say you have
some data structure,
and you have two randomized operations
that you can do on the data structure.
One of them adds an element to it, and
one takes an element out, right? If both
of these things happen with 50%
probability,
the contents of the data structure will
never get very large.
You would require like, let's say you
want to get a hundred things in the data
structure and then like some garbage
collection routine or some compaction
happens. That would require a one in two
to the one hundred chance to happen if
you're randomly adding and removing
things.
But, if we just temporarily disable the
remove function, then you're guaranteed
to get a whole bunch of adds in a row,
and then you're going to trigger that
compaction routine, right? And so, this
is like a very motivating example, and
it
it's like you want to do this with
everything, including with your fault
injection, right? One of the most common
mistakes that in the early days, before
we did this automatically, the customers
would make is they would say, "Ah, I
want my code to be maximum powerful, so
I want to turn on every single fault."
And the problem is there are some faults
that will hide bugs, right? Like imagine
there's a bug where your program gets
into some really bad state, but if you
restart the program, the bug goes away.
Well, now if we are doing a fault that
occasionally kills nodes, that can hide
that bug, right? And so what you
actually want to do is sometimes run
with killing nodes completely turned
off, because that might save you from
some bug.
And so it's it's exactly the same with
everything else and with what kinds of
requests you generate and every other
kind of behavior that you want to
provoke in the system. Now,
it's still possible to get this wrong,
it's still possible to overlook things.
And so that's why we come back to like
the the sometimes assertions, the
logging, that kind of stuff. If you know
the transaction rollbacks are an
important situation, you should be
adding, you know, a sometimes assertion
or a log to your rollback function, and
then we should be looking at every test
run and saying, "Did we make rollbacks
happen?" And if not, that should be a
red test failure, right? It It could
mean that your program has changed.
Maybe you accidentally disabled the
rollback function, and that's, you know,
now we found a real bug. But it could
also mean that the tests are weak,
right? It could mean that for whatever
reason we're not making transactions
rollback enough, and that could be very,
very important information.
>> Mhm. Mhm. So, in that example of the
transaction rollback, you know, the
other trigger event was a leader
election, right? So, again, how do you
draw the correlation of what's happening
at the lowest bits and bytes level to at
the more application level?
How do you say that, hey, that actually
is a leader election?
>> Yeah, yeah, yeah. So, the easiest way to
do this actually, so the way that
requires the least investment from a
user is you just look at lines of code.
Every line of code in your program has a
purpose.
Some of the lines of code are very
boring. They run all the time, right?
The code that like logs a string. That
probably is running all the time in your
program. And so
we are going to see it running all the
time and we are quickly going to get
bored of it.
>> Across all the programs. Because the
analytics will be an external event or
external service.
>> Totally. Totally true. But anything that
runs rarely, that runs only sometimes,
or that runs in very specific
conditions, or that runs
You could also have, for example, a line
of code
that very commonly runs together with
some other line of code, but very, very
rarely runs by itself. That could be
something very interesting. So you're
not just looking at which lines of code
run or don't run at all, but you're
actually also looking at the
correlations between them and when they
run together with each other or not and
and what orders they run and so on. And
this is a kind of
analysis that human beings are very bad
at doing, but it's a kind of analysis
that AI is actually very good at doing,
machine learning and so on. And so you
can sort of look at the history of
what the software has done
and then ask, is this novel? Like, is
this interesting? Is this something This
is very similar to what I've seen before
or is it very different from what I've
seen before? And then you can use that
as an input into where you want to
continue testing.
>> Mhm. So are you using AI ML here to do
the correlation?
>> Yeah. Yeah, yeah. We actually find
It's It's funny. For many, many, many
application domains and in many, many,
many situations, it's overkill. Like
Like you you actually find almost all
the bugs with much simpler methods once
you've got some decent randomness in
there and some decent fault injection.
But we are currently doing some very
cool research with this that we think is
going to is going to drastically
drastically improve our our results,
which I cannot quite talk about yet, but
we will be we'll
we'll we'll probably be announcing it
probably announcing it soon.
>> Could you give us a hint?
>> Uh I've I've said too much.
>> Sure. Sure.
I got I got to wait to see it. What
about limitations? I mean, cost sounds
like one, but when would this be a
completely inapplicable or
ill-advised case?
>> Yeah, great question. I think the costs
people often focus on costs, and I think
that this is like very silly. Of course,
I would say that, but but no, I think it
is very I think it is very silly because
basically because what people are
currently doing is costing them so much.
Like you go and you talk to
engineering leaders, engineering
managers,
and you're like, "How much money do you
spend on testing?" And they're like,
"Oh, we don't spend any money at all. We
don't buy any tools." And then you're
like, "Okay,
how much time do your engineers spend
answering pages, triaging production
issues, writing tests, maintaining tests
that are broken, like blah blah blah."
And they're like, "Oh my god, they spend
all their time doing these things." I'm
like, "Okay, great. How many engineers
do you have? How much you paying them?"
Like you're spending a huge amount on on
the on the stuff, right? But people
don't people don't always think about
that way, but they are. And I think
that's one of the challenges is is to
make people realize that they're already
spending millions and millions and
millions of dollars on this.
In terms of what
is a bad fit, I think the main things
right now are number one,
if your program is basically just like
a straight line. In some sense, if it's
very easy to test in a conventional way
because there's not a lot of
concurrency, there's not a lot of like
network chatter, right? It's just like a
small stateless function that does
something, and you can write some unit
tests for it pretty easily.
That probably doesn't justify the the
pain and hassle of trying to test it
this way. If you're running on exotic
hardware, like we certainly cannot
support you today. And if you're using a
vast number of third-party external
dependencies, that's something that
we're going to have a very hard time for
now dealing with because we haven't
written a mock for every single one of
them yet.
I would say those are the main
categories of limitations.
>> I want to contrast it with one
I don't want to call it technique, but
one different idea. If, let's say,
programmers or libraries or developers
could annotate or or inject annotations
in their code base,
which actually explicitly was able to
assign error probabilities.
How compatible would that be with what
you're doing and how much would that
alleviate that initial pain?
>> I think that's a very interesting idea.
So,
one thing
that we actually do encourage our
customers to do. If you're If you're
thinking about annotating, one thing
that I think is a very, very powerful
technique
is something called bugification.
And the idea of bugification is
suppose you have some code which usually
does one thing,
but very rarely could do something else,
right? For example,
it could be like writing to a disk,
right? Usually it writes all the data to
the disk, but you know, as every systems
programmer has learned the hard way,
sometimes it writes some of the data to
the disk and gives you a special return
code that says, "Hey, I only wrote some
of the data." You know, by the way, net-
networks work the same way, right?
>> Well, well, usually flush and fsync are
actually not on by default, so.
>> Well, that's true, too. Yeah. Right, so
Right, anytime you have something like
this that usually does one thing, but
very rarely does something else,
if it's actually great, if you're the
one maintaining that code, to basically
add a little macro around it or add a
little add a little thing, annotation,
which is, "Hey, if I'm running in test,
I'm going to do the rare thing on
purpose sometimes. I'm going to roll a
random number, and maybe 10% of the time
I'm just not going to write all the
data. Or like 10% of the time this thing
is going to throw an error, even though
it doesn't have to. Just to test what
happens on the other side. Like is
somebody catching that error correctly?
Is somebody handling that return value
correctly? That can drastically
accelerate bug discovery, as well.
>> Yeah. Cool.
Switching back to real world examples, I
heard about Ethereum's uh you know the
most effective two, and uh you also
mentioned Wolf stream.
What were some of the most trickiest
kind of scariest bugs that you helped
them uncover?
>> Uh specifically for Ethereum, or for for
anybody?
>> Uh I'll also want to bring up Wolf
stream because you mentioned earlier.
>> Yeah, yeah, yeah. For Ethereum,
I think the scariest bug we found in
Ethereum, yeah, I can talk about it now
because it's long ago been fixed. We
found a very, very scary
denial-of-service bug,
which I believe was actually in their
protocol.
And they had to they had to change their
protocol to address Their former head of
security was the one who's telling us
about this. He basically said that it
would have qualified for the very
highest tier of their bug bounties.
It was a bug that would allow you to
essentially DDoS the Ethereum blockchain
very easily by sending certain
maliciously crafted messages to nodes.
You could basically cause them to shut
down, or like start using 100% CPU and
not doing anything else, or or something
like that. It was pretty
pretty alarming. One of the very first
really scary bugs we found was for
MongoDB.
This was a This was a huge win for us
and for and for them and for our
relationship together.
We had been collaborating with them, but
in like a very
Our thing was brand new, and it was
experimental, and they were trying it
out, and like you know it was sort of
like, "Hey, let's just see how this
goes." Not like serious or anything.
And then, right before they were going
to ship a major release,
we found a
very rare, but very severe data
corruption bug in their WiredTiger
storage engine,
which could basically corrupt completely
arbitrary data in any instance.
And, you know, it was something it was
very rare and it was very hard to make
happen.
But, with the perfect determinism of
DST, we could make it happen as much as
they wanted and enable them to debug it
really, really efficiently. And so, that
was like a very cool win for them and
for us. And that bug has been written up
in extensive detail by one of their
engineers both on our blog and also on
their Jira. I can provide a link for
that if you want.
>> Yes, please.
>> Cool. It's a really good one. Uh it's
WiredTiger bug number 9500. I still
remember the number.
Um
>> What was the trigger for this bug? I
mean, what was the rare trigger that
would have made this bug happen?
>> Yeah, I'm trying to remember the exact
details. This was a few years ago, but
basically it involved it involved their
storage engine and their storage engine
is like a highly, highly concurrent
thing, right? Storage engines have to be
highly concurrent because disks are very
slow.
And so, you need a lot of throughput and
a lot of latency hiding in order to have
a good performance storage engine.
But, you also don't want to take like a
ton of locks everywhere because if you
do that, then like write operations
targeting different parts of your
database could block each other and that
would be bad for performance, too.
And so, much of the difficulty of
writing a storage engine is you're
trying to hide all the weird performance
characteristics and
weird abstractions of a disk and make it
just like appear like a very uniform
right? Even when you have operations
that could logically depend on each
other or not.
And I think we found a bug that involved
like
there was some lock that should have
been taken that wasn't, but it only
happened if there was a compaction
occurring at the same time that
something else happened and you needed
like a particular shape of query and it
was like I'll send you the write up.
It's like a pretty It's a pretty gnarly
one. Like I'm a I used to be a database
guy and I like I looked at this bug and
I was like, "Oh my god, I would like
yeah, I would never
I would not know how to fix this. It was
It was pretty bad. I'm trying to think
of other good
really scary bugs that we found for
people. So, we've done a bunch of
testing for NATS, which is It's one of
the Linux Foundation projects or CNCF
projects. They're sort of a
a distributed sort of software-defined
network and they also have a bunch of
like cool storage primitives and
consensus primitives and stuff like
that. We found a bug in their raft
implementation, which could which I
think they also wrote up for our blog.
It's a really cool bug. It requires
several things to go wrong like a node
has to get excluded from the cluster
right when something is happening and
then it gets restarted and it comes back
and it thinks it's the you know, it's
like one of these classic distributed
systems bugs.
Yeah, I mean like there's there's no
shortage of crazy bug stories around
here. A lot of our customers like have
fun writing them up for us. So, there's
actually a decent number of these on our
blog.
>> Oh, but thank you. Thank you. Can you
share some metrics around how you
quantify
I guess uh
I don't want to use the ROI word, but
you know, once they see it before they
see how do you kind of quantify this?
>> Yeah, so the the customer who's done the
most quantification for us was actually
So, they did their own internal
study and analysis of their use of us
and they basically found I think the
results actually surprised them a little
bit. They actually they they surprised
us too. They had in one period of time a
hundred
really very significant release
blocking, could have done something
quite bad in the real world, bugs
introduced in their development process.
Right? I should I should be really clear
here. These are bugs that came nowhere
close to getting to customers, right?
These were all fixed and like is
like really good at this stuff, which
and I think this like the fact that they
are studying this and quantifying this
really shows you how seriously they take
it. But basically, of those 100 bugs, 77
were only found by us.
Which
which is pretty cool. And then, here's
the next part.
Of those bugs, they found that the
average time to fix them
was massively lower if we found the bug.
They were like fixed in half as much
time and they were able to be fixed by
much more junior engineers.
>> Is that because your discovery would
identify all the scenarios that would
need to be triggering that bug as
opposed to guessing what's going on?
>> Yeah, that's a huge part of it is is we
have the determinism, right? And so we
can just replay that bug, right? Like so
much of the hard part of debugging is
you never have all the information you
need and you may not be able to get that
bug to happen again, right? Like an
analogy I really like to use is it's
like a police investigation, right? Like
when a server crashes, like you have to
put up the yellow tape, so like nobody's
going to step on that crime scene and
like ruin the evidence or something.
It's like anything that you do in
production could
potentially make the bug go away and
then you don't And so really senior
engineers get good at guessing and they
get good at like they know these systems
like the back of their hand and they're
like, "Oh, I've seen the I saw this one
time 3 years ago. I know what this
Right? Like
But as soon as you have determinism,
it's like you're doing that police
investigation, but you have a time
machine. You can just go back in time
and watch the accident happen. Like
watch the murder happen and now you know
who did it. That's so different. It's
such a huge change. It actually implies
really big changes in how all parts of
the SDLC work, right? Like if you think
about it, people log way too much.
Like, people log so much data. Like,
this is why observability vendors make
so much money. Like, it's all it's all
log storage. But, like, why do people
log so much data? People log so much
data because they know that some issue
could happen. And if it's a one in a
million issue, but it's really
important, they may not be able to make
it happen again. And so, you better hope
that you have that log statement in
there so that you can like put together
the clues and figure it out. But again,
if you have a time machine, you don't
need to log all that data. You just go
back to before the bug and you and you
look at it happen. Or you take a core
dump at the right time. Or you or you go
dynamically enable your logs right
before the bug hits and then you turn
them off again afterwards. There's like
such a different attitude and a
different approach that like becomes
possible once you have this capability.
>> I'm, yeah. It's awesome.
What's getting in the way of adoption?
>> Oh, I think just that it's brand new.
Like I said, the very first people that
we know of who were doing this started
doing it in 2010.
And it was all hidden inside this
company until 2015.
And then,
word got out, but it was only possible
for extremely fanatical, crazy people to
do it because the barrier to adoption
was so high.
Right? And still, a lot of people wanted
to do it because it was very effective.
But like, we came out of stealth and
launched this company 1 year ago. So, we
are really, really brand new. Right? So,
most of the people who we talk to, they
just like I mean, I think we sound like
crazy people to them. Like, you know,
they're like, you know, we're trying to
we're trying to explain to them there's
this like completely different way to
have confidence in your software and to
and to get way more confidence in it and
to save yourself tons of time. And
as with anything, like, the computer
industry, the tech industry loves to
think that we are very, very
forward-looking. But actually, people
are creatures of habit. And that's
especially true about developer tools,
right? And so, I think a lot of this is
just like we need a little bit of time
to like move the industry in this new
direction.
>> I think it's only now that
time-traveling debuggers are kind of
taking on, so
>> That's right. That's right. And that
technology's been around for 10, 20
years. Yeah, 30 years, 30 years, yeah.
GDB was able to do this like decades
ago. Yeah.
>> Yeah. Looking back at integration,
right?
Now, obviously, I'm guessing if I was a
a front-end developer, I may not be as
motivated to get on DST. But same time,
on the other other extreme, if I was a
kernel developer or a database vendor or
a storage developer,
this seems extremely, extremely
valuable, right?
In that spectrum, when would be the
sweet spot to kind of start considering
this?
>> Right. So, we've actually started seeing
really a lot of traction with
application developers, but so far it's
specifically in the sector of fintech
and finance and blockchain stuff.
They're definitely doing something more
abstract, more high-level than a
database developer or a kernel or a
systems developer. But the thing is that
what they're doing is so important, and
it's like so important that it not make
mistakes, that that justifies this like
much higher level of scrutiny.
So, we recently began working with Ramp,
which the corporate card, and they, you
know, they have a service that like
decides whether authorize charges on the
card, and it's really bad if that like
fails to respond to a request or it
authorizes it twice or that would be not
good. And so, they really want to test
it very, very effectively, and and
they've been doing that with us. We
recently also started working with a
large hedge fund. I can't say their
name, but it's a big one. And similar
kind of situation, right? Like they're
moving hundreds of millions of dollars
around. They really care that that works
correctly, and they really care that
every operation is is running in the
right way.
>> Looking forward, I think the big
buzzword now AI.
With AI writing so much code and if you
see in the last few days, it's just it's
coding for hours and generating, you
know, millions and
so much of the code, right? How do you
see, you know, all that all that
impacting security bugs, vulnerabilities
and uh
Sounds Sounds like opportunity.
>> Yeah.
I think so. I think basically you know,
AI can write a lot of code now. And the
thing is that
people are very tempted to just sort of
ship it, right? And to not look too
carefully at it, which is not a very
good idea if you're in a certain line of
work. And so
I think it is a huge opportunity for
people trying to develop more
sophisticated approaches to software
verification, right? It really
highlights
writing code is no longer the
bottleneck. Actually, writing code was
never the bottleneck, but people thought
it was. But like
now writing code is really really really
not the bottleneck, right? The
bottleneck is making sure it does the
right thing. And that's much harder.
>> Yeah. I mean, writing is not reading, it
is.
>> Yeah, exactly. Exactly. Well, that's the
other problem with AI, of course, is
like it generates a whole bunch of code
for you and then as soon as you want to
modify anything about it, you're
basically starting from scratch.
>> How you seeing adapting to this? Like,
you know, do you have to change your
approach and how you, you know, approach
companies?
What's your
strategy like now?
>> It hasn't really affected our approach
that much, to be totally honest. Like,
we have a lot of customers who are doing
a lot of AI code generation and they're
using us to test the results, right? And
I probably that segment of our customers
will continue to grow over time.
Nothing about what we're doing has to
change that fundamentally, right? To it
to accommodate this use case.
You know, it just means there's more
bugs for us to find.
>> Fair enough. Talking about bugs, you
mentioned was it who had a a high
bug bounty? I'm sorry, for Ethereum.
>> That was Ethereum, yeah. Yeah, yeah.
>> Did you guys qualify for that bug bounty
or
>> No, we we since we were a vendor for
them, we didn't we didn't qualify for. I
I wish I wish it would have been it
would have been a lot of money.
No, we in the early days of the company,
we actually thought about using bug
bounties as the primary source of
revenue, right? Cuz like some of them
get pretty high.
And this thing is actually quite good at
finding security bugs, too, that that
human beings sometimes miss.
And so, that was certainly a thing we
thought about. In the end, we thought
that that was a little bit adversarial.
And that we would rather be embedded
with our customer's engineering team and
like making them successful and like
improving their lives, making it easier
for them to do their job. We thought
that in the long term, that would lead
to better customer relationships than
this like come in from the outside and
claim bounties model.
But I I assume somebody's going to be
using
either DST or AI or something else to
claim bug bounties very soon.
>> Mhm, fair enough. No, no, I I'd say it's
a
exciting kind of future out there. As we
wrap up in closing thoughts, what advice
would you give to our listeners about
improving their own testing practices or
evolving their, you know, platforms to
get ready for DST?
>> Right. It's really The thing I said
towards the start of this is I think the
single most important piece of advice.
Anytime you see a bug in production, any
single time,
it is two bugs.
It is two bugs. It is a bug in your
code, but it's also a bug in your tests.
And you should demand more from your
tests. You should cultivate the attitude
that it is unacceptable
for things to go wrong in production.
And that if a thing does go wrong in
production, you should be asking
yourself, what could we have done
differently
that would mean that we found this ahead
of time?
>> Awesome. For all those who want to learn
more, how How they do so and where?
>> Oh, yeah. There's a lot of people who've
written good stuff about this. We have
some material on our website
antithesis.com. The other people who
have talked the loudest and the most
about DST, the FoundationDB team, has
written a bunch of stuff about this.
They're now at Apple and and a lot of
them are at Snowflake, but they've
written a ton of good stuff. The
FoundationDB paper that came out
a few years ago and was in SIGMOD is
very good. I can send you a link to
that. It's got a whole section on how we
did DST.
The people at TigerBeetle have written
some really good stuff about this.
They've done a very good job at it. So,
I think those are some pretty good
resources and then I give a talk at
StrangeLoop back in 2015 about the
FoundationDB DST approach. So, that's
almost 10 years ago now, but it still
still has some good stuff.
>> Nice. Thank you. Before we wrap up, is
there anything that we haven't covered
that you'd like to share um for our
listeners?
>> Nope. I think uh this was a ton of fun.
Thank you so much.
>> Thank you. Thank you. Will, thanks for
being on the show. Looking forward to
seeing you live.
>> Haha. Cool.
>> Cheers.
>> Thanks for listening to SE Radio, an
educational program brought to you by
IEEE Software Magazine. For more about
the podcast, including other episodes,
visit our website at SE-Radio.net.
To provide feedback, you can comment on
each episode on the website or reach us
on LinkedIn, Facebook, Twitter, or
through our Slack channel at
SE-Radio.slack.com.
You can also email us at
team@se-radio.net.
This and all other episodes of SE Radio
is licensed under Creative Commons
License 2.5.
Thanks for listening.